Today, I sat down with PBJ, the founder of Purple.
Purple is a first-in-class crypto perpetual exchange launching on the Monad blockchain.
I was fortunate enough to have this conversation with PBJ shortly ahead of the anticipated
Monad and Purple launch this fall.
We discussed perpetual or PERP exchanges and the role they play in crypto markets, Hyperliquid's
recent success, how PERPs could expand to other markets, and what makes Monad unique
in the backdrop of many other new blockchains.
I hope you enjoy our conversation.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions
and do not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures.
Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in this podcast.
You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific inducement
to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only as an expression
of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Cut down by bad mortgage investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will be liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group, AIG, 85 billion dollars.
This is a different kind of market and the Fed is asleep!
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the two mortgage
giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing.
You print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin.
Bitcoin.
TBJ, great to see you.
Thanks for coming on.
Excited to chat today.
Thanks for having me on, Wyatt.
I want to kick off hitting on some of the subject matter you spent a lot of your day
on.
To boil things down, I think a lot gets glossed over in crypto.
People talk about different products, different narratives, and perps or perpetual futures
have undoubtedly been won.
Can you speak to what perps actually are and why people use them?
What are they good for?
Perps are basically a derivative instrument that allows you to speculate or hedge with
leverage on the price action of an asset.
But unlike spot, you don't actually need to hold the underlying instrument.
There's some TradFi parallels like options and futures, but those instruments usually
have an expiration or you have to take delivery.
Perpetuals don't have an expiration, so you can go on holding the instrument as long as
you have margin and are paying your funding.
And why is that attractive to people, whether you're a frequent trader or a typical crypto
user?
What's the draw there?
One of the things that happens in, for example, options is they have expirations, so you'll
have options for, let's say, every month.
What happens there is liquidity gets fragmented.
And perpetual, since there's no real options, you have a lot more liquidity in each of these
instruments.
Each of these markets have just one market for it.
So you just have a better trading experience in terms of slippage and execution.
It's also a lot more simpler for retail traders to understand.
You don't have to do all this crazy Black Scholes math and options math for it.
It's just based on leverage and price action, you have a very easy understanding of what's
happening with the product.
So if price goes up and you have a 5x leverage, you have a 5x return on that and vice versa.
It could go against you and you could get liquidated.
So the simplicity and the liquidity being all in one market makes it a very retail-friendly
product.
And for folks listening, by proxy, how much of crypto trading is happening via perps today
versus via spot or options or any other mechanism?
It's orders of magnitude more.
I think Binance is a good proxy.
I want to say 90-10 or derivatives versus spot.
Again, because you can take leverage and each dollar can go 10 to 50 times in notional,
just the value transacted on derivatives is just a lot higher than spot, similar to traditional
markets where futures markets are in trillions and equities markets might be in billions.
And this is a good segue because I think if you look back historically, at perps and crypto
is a lot of centralized exchange usage, Binance being a big one, obviously.
But more recently, we've seen the emergence of hyperliquid as a major player.
So on the back of that last point, how much of perp trading today is uncentralized exchanges
versus decentralized exchanges?
And how do you think hyperliquid was able to enter this market so effectively where
there was a lot of Binance and centralized exchange usage?
It's still dominated by centralized exchanges.
I don't have the specific numbers, but there's this great analytics dashboard that compares
hyperliquid versus centralized exchanges.
And I think the last time I saw it was between 10 to 15% of Binance, and that's just a single
centralized exchange.
Hyperliquid has done a lot of great things.
I've talked about this in some of my Twitter posts, but they were there at the right time.
So what usually derives trading has happened, let's say Bitmax, Biobit, Binance, FTX have
all been leaders there.
Around 21, 22, when the FTX saga unfolded, people were just tired of trading on centralized
exchanges and taking on this custodian risk.
Hyperliquid founders have talked about that.
There was just a missing part in the market where there was a decentralized exchange there
to fill that void.
DYDX was going through these numerous debates from Starkware to their own L1, and people
were just lost in maze there.
So they timed the market really well.
And then they really hyper-focused on the product.
So they just wanted it to be something where it just worked like field transactions or
gas bikes, or needing to sign everything with a metamask wallet.
Just felt like it was trading on a centralized exchange.
I think the really cool things that they did was because they had a background in market
making, they understood primitives that worked, which is a central order book.
I think if you look around the space, there wasn't really a chain you can put that on.
That was a general purpose chain.
You necessarily had to build your own chain, and that's what they did.
So the other part that they included there was the HLP.
Again, you can see GMX popularized that with the GLP.
Jupyter also used that, but both of those products were for AMMs, and there are a lot
more programmatic setter, don't forget it.
HLP changed it a little bit with the fact that because they had this market making experience,
they were able to market on their own claw.
They were using passive LP liquidity there.
That basically short-circuited the need for market makers and allowed them to have deeper
liquidity so people could trade in size on a decentralized exchange.
And eventually that also helped them list tokens faster, which is like a huge thing
for an exchange to be attractive.
Again, to close out that point, they also made some really good decisions like prioritizing
cancels on their blockchain consensus or having custom opcodes for funding and solvency
checks.
Again, this is the kind of things and knowledge that they brought with their prior experience
of, hey, this is stuff that we would like to have in our own decentralized exchange.
And if we're going to be the de facto market maker, we don't want to get run over by professionals
because of the lack of information or whatever else, so we should prioritize cancels.
And then I think the final stroke of genius was they were a perp dex only, and then they
realized that, you know what, we can't just be a single app blockchain.
We've seen how that plays out with these L2 app chains and other products.
They added this sidecar EVM, which allowed them to escape that glass ceiling of an app
chain.
So we'll see how that plays out for them.
But I think those decisions that they've made along the way have helped them become as successful
as they are.
Yeah, I think that's a great overview.
I do want to circle back to one point you made.
I think that in the wake of the FTX collapse, call it the six months after fall 2022, which
was in that window hyperliquid launch, like you mentioned, crypto was at its peak level
of distrust of centralized financial institutions, which is saying a lot, obviously, for the
crypto industry.
And there was a great timing aspect there that probably allowed something like hyperliquid
to get on that growth trajectory, which they've continued and exceeded.
Do you think that skepticism of centralized institutions and at the same time preference
for decentralized finance among a certain subset of crypto users is still present such
that you'll have more players like this potentially emerge?
Or do you think there's been some sort of reversion to comfort using centralized exchanges?
I think the world is more moving towards on-chain.
I think the parity between centralized exchanges and decentralized exchanges is going down
significantly.
So one of the reasons why most of this trading used to happen on these centralized exchanges
was faster.
You could actually market make.
There wasn't the primitives that market makers expected, like a central limit order book
or blockchain that was fast enough to market make on these order books.
So as these decentralized exchanges are being built on these faster blockchains, you start
to see even the central exchanges are like, hey, licensing, KYC, regulated exchange type
of trajectory when we can also start our own decentralized exchange.
So I think the world is heading more towards on-chain 24-7 trading, where people just wall
it in a stablecoin versus I need to submit my passport ID.
I need to do X, Y, and Z before I can withdraw my funds.
That's just, I think, a relic of the past and we'll start to see more volumes shifted
towards decentralized exchanges.
That's a great segue, though, when you're speaking about better systems on better blockchains.
Why are you building this product?
Why now and why on Monad?
I think there's been lots of great tweets about this, but the two things from crypto
that feel like how a definitive product market fit is perps and stablecoins.
When there's a new one that launches, one of the things you need to make sure is it's
You've seen this.
There's a bunch of stablecoin L1s launching or HFT style L1s.
On these HFT style L1s, you need a flagship product that brings user interest, capital
and trading activity to generate fees.
The best product for that is Perpdex.
So when we were initially thinking about this product, we surveyed the landscape to see
what is out there.
And there really isn't, for one, a clob on a general purpose L1.
Any clob that you see is on an app chain or an L2.
And the second part being there wasn't an EVM L1 that we could build this on.
And that part is very important because no matter how you slice it, the EVM has become
the JavaScript of blockchain technology.
To get comparison.
If you look at the number of assets, collaterals that are on the EVM chain, the amount of developer
support, the amount of infrastructure support is all on EVM chains.
So when you think about it that way, the only chain that this makes sense on is on Monad.
People have tried to do this on an SVM on Solana, but there's some issues with Solana
where it's constrained by accounts and the need for cranking on a clob.
And that's something that EVM does not have.
So we were like, okay, obviously Monad is going to be launching soon.
We talked to the founders and there is other EVM chains that are high frequency all once.
But the way they go about reducing latency is by centralizing.
And Monad did not take any shortcuts there.
They were rebuilding the system from roundup.
So they were talking about rewriting the firmware for their hardware, completely overhauling
their database.
So they were doing things the right way.
And when we thought about building this, we're like, who do we expect to be around for the
next 10 years?
And it made perfect sense to build this on Monad.
And to go into the guts of it, we think that the gas budget that it offers, the latency
that Monad has, it was perfect for building a order book style perpdex.
And that's what we're building now.
It's very helpful.
I want to get a sense of your mapping here, but who do you look at as the primary customer
that you guys will be serving post-launch?
Is it folks who might otherwise be using Binance or a hyperliquid?
Is it EVM users who are going to be converted to bigger perp traders or maybe perp traders
on the EVM using a product they don't love as much?
Or who do you look at as being that target audience?
When you're building an exchange, you have to build for both market makers and takers.
For us, it was very important when we were building this exchange to, one, build a very
efficient exchange.
I know we're getting into the weeds of this, but it's really important to make sure that
you're making the right trade-offs here because unlike building on an app chain or an L2 where
you control the sequencer, when you build on a general purpose L1, you have to worry
about the consensus and the gas budget.
One of the things that we were very specific about is makers posting and cancelling on
the order book should be extremely gas efficient.
If you're able to do that and Monad does its job, it should make it really easy for
market makers to make on this.
And that's basically how we optimize this problem, is to make it so that it's the most
market maker-friendly EVM club out there.
As far as our user base, I think there's already a hunger for perps.
There's a ton of interest on hyperliquid, lighter.
There's honestly nothing but perp chatter on crypto Twitter.
Everybody knows and understands this.
One of the other benefits of building on an L1 is that they come with their own incentivized
community, their day one users, and that's great.
So initially it will help Monad community and users start trading with their assets
on purple.
And eventually we're going to start attracting people outside the Monad ecosystem that want
to come trade on our product because we offer a distinctive order feature set or different
types of orders or different types of collateral.
Yeah, understood.
This is a blunt comparison, but you would want a DEX on an EVM general purpose L1 the
same way that you want Apple Pay, like it's compatible with a lot of the other financial
things you're doing if you're a DeFi user.
Exactly.
When I think about if I'm starting a new L1, you need the perp exchange, you need that
spot exchange, probably an AMM, you need some sort of lending protocols.
I like thinking of it in Thinkasib or Biology, one of those people talked about how blockchains
are countries.
You need these primitives there.
You need the banking system, you need the foreign exchange, you need the stock market.
And these primitives have to be there in the beginning for any other type of activity to
kickstart on that blockchain.
Outside of the EVM, do you think Solana has gotten that ecosystem mix correct?
Or would you have criticisms of what they've built or places where you think they could
have a better experience?
I think they are definitely the ones that have made the biggest impact.
I think people have a very short memory, but Solana has done some incredible things
as well.
They have Jupyter, they have Phoenix, Pomp recently, they have Camino and all these other
products that are Solana specific.
They're not just copy and pasted from the EVM.
So that's one of the things that they went through, which is a lot of road pains where
you needed to learn a completely new programming language, a completely new EVM.
So they had to really chew glass for the first four years.
And of course, they went through the whole FTX debacle.
So it's truly incredible what they have done and accomplished.
And they seem to be going even stronger now with the Ansa and Fire Dancer.
So it would definitely not count them out.
I think Hyperliquid has started pushing everything off to move faster and focus on revenue generating
products.
And that's definitely a good thing for our whole ecosystem.
Yeah, agreed.
Going back a little bit to how people will use Purple and other perp exchanges.
What assets are heavily traded here?
I've been maybe a light user, so you see Bitcoin, ETH unsurprisingly get a lot of usage.
But will this be virtually any asset?
Is it a fairly long tail or how do you expect people to use the platform in that sense?
I think the majors are going to be there, obviously.
And then again, benefit of building an ecosystem is when those new coins launch there, you
will have their listings and probably higher open interest and liquidity for those.
Longer term, I think more and more assets will start getting booted and deployed on
chain.
So obviously, if there's an Oracle and market makers willing to quote, there's no edge
in listing.
It's pretty much like a race to the bottom there, where you have to list as fast as possible
if there's a token of interest.
Whether that's going to be like the stocks or whatever, I just don't know.
I think Ostium is doing a great job of that.
But there's challenges there.
What do you do on the weekend?
So you have to wind down markets and start them up again.
I don't think you can do a clob there.
But there's other products, I think SuperState is doing a great job there, where they're
doing primary issuance on chain.
And I think as TradFi and more finance starts moving on chain, those products will be available
for trading 24-7, there will be Oracles for that.
And again, one of the really cool things that HyperLiquid did was HIP3, allow anybody
to deploy perp markets.
So eventually, we would like to get to a steady state where if there is a perp market that
we haven't deployed and somebody else wants to deploy, and they have an Oracle market
maker service for that, they should be able to do that.
We want to provide that base level infrastructure for them and the order above permitted so
they can deploy it and have trading happen on it.
And to your knowledge, are most of these trader behaviors on these perp exchanges fairly
simple one directional levers long exposure, or short on the other end?
Or is there usually a more holistic or sophisticated strategy involved when you look at the typical
user?
Unfortunately, it's just so nuanced, it depends on the asset, it depends on the strategy,
it depends on the market conditions.
So generally, you can think institutions are probably focused on blue chips and majors,
and they're trying to hedge their exposure.
Retail are probably more focused on these longer tail assets where they want high volatility,
be up for market listings, upside from those products.
So it truly depends on the market.
And then of course, if there's some fed funding rate cut or whatever, then there's going to
be massive volatility in the market where everybody's trying to get out of position
or get into a position.
So it's truly nuanced.
But the cool thing about this is it's globally participatable, anybody can with a wallet
get on and speculate or hedge their positions.
And that's the beauty of decentralized finance.
And to that point about it being globally accessible, is this mostly desktop behavior
mobile or how are people accessing currently?
Yeah, I think the power traders are all still on desktop.
We've talked to a bunch of these traders.
So one of the things that they would love on mobile is a way to get notifications or
close position or add margin.
There's lots of nice tools for the ground bots and whatnot.
But the newer people that are getting onboarded, the PVP dot trade people, the Axiom wallet
traders, they're all mobile first.
So again, I think Table Stakes is building a desktop interface and having different UIs
for retail professionals and those types of personas.
But eventually, either that's going to be involving partnering with a wallet provider
or building your own mobile app because that's a crucial market base that is new and interesting
perhaps that you're not going to get from just desktop based trading experiences.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Do you think over time, obviously, we see that a large proportion of crypto trading
is already perp based to your point.
Do you think over time we see that evolve to almost all of crypto trading?
Do you think that the split between spot and perps change is in favor of perps?
Or do we see any other notable change to the market structure?
You still need the spot price.
You just need two different prices for this whole thing to work, for the funding rate
to be calibrated.
But I think the split might continuously stay closer to 80-20 or 90-10.
I think the TAM of the whole industry is growing.
The perps trading TAM is growing really fast and alongside with that spot will grow as
well because you need that settling asset for the funding rates and the prices to track.
It's not going to be 100% one thing.
A durable inherently needs something to derive the price from.
But I think just the general market is going to continue growing.
More trading will continue to move on chain.
Understood. I'm very excited for other asset classes to take on this form factor as well.
Well, you mentioned about what Ostium is doing and having equities, even if there's a growing
period there.
Yeah, absolutely.
Again, Robinhood has teased that a little bit.
I think even those equity markets understand that if they can get this on chain, some version
of it, there's just a global capital market that is hungry to trade those assets.
Today, how do you trade US stock equities if you are in, let's say, India or Nigeria
or China?
If those people could somehow get exposure to that, that's just a lot bigger capital
base.
I'm not sure the people at those companies would love to have that access to that capital.
Yeah, definitely.
Not to mention the traders.
I want to close on a couple of points that I was keen to pick your brain about and get
some insights.
First off, why should people get excited or care about Monad?
I think there are reasons that are maybe a bit more obvious in the sense of a very fast
EVM general purpose chain, close to Ethereum, but much more performant, obviously.
But I'd love your perspective.
Is there anything you would add to that against the current backdrop of things we're seeing
like hyperliquid plasma, other chains?
I think it goes back to that point, I mean, it's just not been possible to build a fully
on chain central limit order book on an EVM before.
That's a very key point because if you just see what was possible with GMX on Arbitrum,
there were just all these nice composability benefits that came about with it.
It's really exciting to see what will come about with what we're building in terms of
the composability benefits and how people use it.
Monad allows us to do things that haven't been possible before.
The other benefit of building on this L1 is this is the beginning of it.
So they're going to continue improving the blockchain.
They're going to make it faster.
There's going to be more gas.
Transaction costs are going to go down.
And more excitingly, they're also going to, again, because of products like hyperliquid
pushing them, try to figure out how to do priority transactions like how can we get
purple to have cancel priority in our consensus or do private transactions.
Because again, Tempo and these other blockchains have been talking about allowing people to
do private transactions.
So the benefit of building on an L1 is every EIP or MIP, if you want to call it, Monad
improvement proposal ends up helping every protocol being built on that chain.
So in essence, we have 50 to 100 high level blockchain researchers at Category Labs working
to improve the chain.
And we can just focus on building the best perpetual exchange out there and get trading
activity.
And on a related note, from your view, looking at the community, what's gotten people excited
about purple?
Where is their anticipation and where is there the excitement?
I think we've talked to a whole bunch of diverse set of users with us, retail users, whales,
protocols, and whatnot.
For retail users, it's pretty simple.
They're like, wow, I can have an airdrop on Monad, I can use those assets right there.
I don't have to bridge it to another ecosystem to go trade on hyperliquid, for example.
For your advanced users, there's pain points.
Hyperliquid's done a great job, but they're doing a ton of things.
They're doing an L1, an EVM, a perp exchange.
That's a lot of stuff that they're focused on.
We want to basically fill the gaps that they can't fill.
One of them is advanced features like hidden liquidity or iceberg orders.
The other thing that we can do is allow for newer collateral types.
Again, going back to the point of building on an EVM chain is it'll be nice if you can
allow users to use a non-USDC collateral.
One of the easiest things that we can do is a one-click basis trade.
Let's just say Kaito, for example.
If you state Kaito and you hold it, you get these future airdrops.
The problem that you have today is Kaito price fluctuates.
The real benefit that you're looking to have is just these future airdrops and you just
want to lock in the price of Kaito.
If you want to lock that in today, what you need to do is get some more USDC, go to a
DEX or a central exchange that's Kaito, open the 1X short.
Now you have to maintain that short position, whether it's adding margin or funding or
whatever else.
What we want to allow people to do is use that state Kaito as collateral to do a 1X
short Kaito perp.
What that in essence does is it basically gives you unlimited liquidation price because
positions perfectly hedge.
The underlying collateral balances out the perp leg.
Obviously, we're not going to allow a 100% edge, but even if you give it 80, 90% LTV,
it's still a huge benefit for most people because they get to hold a token, put in future
staking rewards, airdrops and whatnot.
That's the cool thing about building on a general purpose LL1 is there's going to be
more collateral types.
We can possibly allow people to do these types of one-click basis trading.
Then the last thing I was going to say is we also have these vaults similar to HLP.
There's going to be the LP vault, but unlike HLP, again, because we're building on a general
purpose LL1, we get support from Fireblocks.
What that allows us to do is you can hedge your risk on central exchange.
Basically, a jelly-jelly situation is a lot harder to happen on our product because let's
just say there's a new listing and the vault is taking one direction on our perp dex.
It would then take the opposite direction on a central exchange because we can use Fireblocks.
It just makes the product a lot more resilient and there's not these issues of potential
backgrounds on the protocol.
Completely understood.
I like that Kaito example you gave.
It's like anyone who's tried to maintain points exposure, anything like that, has come
across that scenario in crypto where you want to be exposed to that, but you don't want
to have the full volatility of the underlying asset.
Exactly.
PVJ, man, thanks for coming on.
It's been a pleasure chatting and hopefully we can do it again soon.
Awesome.
Thank you for having me.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To learn more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc and to listen to all of our podcast episodes,
please visit castleisland.vc slash podcast or just click on the tab on our website.
Thanks for listening.